翻译：1149761294
该视频是关于SNES原理系列的第二部分
This video is part 2 in a series about Super Nintendo Entertainment System features.
我们将讨论对象是什么 对象的属性如何存储 和其他相关内容
We'll talk about what objects are, how Object Attribute Memory works, and everything else
object related.
首先 科普一些术语
First, a little bit of terminology needs cleared up.
这听起来有点迂腐 但这就是这样
This is going to sound a little pedantic, but that's because it is.
这些在屏幕上移动的东西叫什么？
What are these things that move around the screen called?
大多数人会说这些是精灵 这种说法从不同方面看时对时错
Most people would say that these are sprites, and that's both correct and incorrect in different
ways.
这些东西有三个部分
There are three parts to these things.
精灵 其他的精灵 和对象
The sprite, the other sprite, and the objects.
实体的抽象通常被叫做精灵
The abstract being of this entity is often called a sprite.
在现代编程语言(尤其是面向对象语言)中 他们被称为对象
In modern programming languages (especially object-oriented ones), these would be called
这就更让人困惑了
objects, which makes this even more confusing.
我们也可以把驱动这个东西的代码看作是精灵指令
We can also think of the code that drives this thing as the sprite instructions.
精灵用来向玩家展示自己的图形通常也被称为精灵
The graphics that a sprite uses to display itself to the player is also commonly called
a sprite.
图片搜索关键词“sprite sheet”可以得到一堆不同游戏中的精灵图像
Doing an image search for 'sprite sheet' results in a bunch of different sprites from different
games.
至于SNES的图形方式 它需要一个对象列表并显示在屏幕上
As for what the Super Nintendo sees graphics-wise, it takes a list of objects and displays them
on the screen.
由于对象的大小和形状非常有限 对象组合在一起才可以组成精灵
Combined together, objects can make up sprites, as the size and shape of objects is very limited.
好了 这些都讲完了 对象到底是什么呢？
Okay, with that out of the way, what exactly are objects?
任何可以独立于背景图层移动的小图像都是对象
Any small graphic that can move independently of the background layers is an object.
对象使用的图形的深度总是4BPP
The graphics that objects use always have a depth of 4 bits-per-pixel, and can use one
而且使用8~15共8个调色板之一
of the eight palettes from 8-15.
它们的大小可以是8x8 16x16 32x32或64x64像素
They can be either 8x8, 16x16, 32x32, or 64x64 pixels in size.
16x32和32x64也可以 但不是任天堂官方支持的
16x32 and 32x64 is also possible, but weren't officially supported by Nintendo.
屏幕上同时只能显示两种尺寸
Only two sizes can be present on screen at one time, as each object only knows whether
因为每个对象只知道自己是“大”还是“小”
it should be 'big' or 'small'.
每个对象需要34位数据来确定其所有属性
Each object requires 34 bits to determine all of its properties.
3位数据表示对象使用的是哪一个调色板
Three bits are used to denote which palette the object is using.
9位数据用于索引VRAM以显示图形块
Nine bits are used to index into VRAM which graphics tiles to display.
如果对象大于8x8像素 那么其它相邻的被用到图块
If the object is larger than 8x8, the other tiles that are used are found by adding 1
会通过横向+0x01 纵向+0x10来得到
to the value to get horizontal neighbors, and 0x10 to get vertical neighbors.
1位被用来确定对象的大小 1位被用来确定是否垂直翻转
One bit is used to determine the object's size, one is used to flip the object vertically,
1位被用来确定是否水平翻转
and one is used to flip it horizontally.
2位被用来确定对象的优先级
Two bits are used to specify the object's priority.
优先级较高的对象会显示在优先级低的对象的上面
Objects with higher priority are displayed on top of other objects with lower priority,
以及某些背景图层
as well as above certain background layers.
最后17位被用来确定对象在屏幕上的位置
The last 17 bits are used for the object's position on the screen.
屏幕大小是256x224像素
The object display screen size is 256x224 pixels.
对象的坐标系原点是画面的左上角
The position of objects are based off of their top left corner relative to the top left corner
of the display area.
所以你可能认为我们需要8位横坐标+8位纵坐标就够了
So you might think we would need 8+8 bits to span all of screen space.
那样基本可以 但是屏幕左侧和上侧会有一个问题
That would be close, but there's an issue with the left and top edges of the screen.
如果只有8位 物体可以部分跑到屏幕的右边缘外面
With only 8 bits, an object could be partially off of the screen on the right edge, but not
但是左边不行
the left edge.
所以多出的1位用于扩展x轴 使物体也可以部分跑到左侧外面
So an extra bit is used for the X axis, so that an object can be partially off the left
side of the screen as well.
对于Y轴来说 这不是一个大问题 因为屏幕只有224像素高
This isn't as big of an issue for the Y axis, since the screen is only 224 pixels high instead
然而 较大的对象不能在不在另一侧露出来的情况下
of 256; however, larger objects can't clip off of the top or bottom of the screen without
在屏幕的顶部或底部部分显示
wrapping around the other side.
所有的这些数据都存储在对象属性内存中(OAM)
All of this data is stored in Object Attribute Memory, or OAM.
这是一小块内存 只有544字节 与CGRAM VRAM WRAM是分开的
This is a small chunk of memory, only 544 bytes, that is separate from CGRAM, VRAM,
or WRAM.
它的空间足够储存128个不同对象的属性
It has enough room to store attributes for 128 different objects.
它分为两个表 我们称它们为表A和表B
It's split into two tables, we'll call them table A and table B.
在表A中 每个对象条目32位宽(4字节)
In table A, each object has an entry 32 bits wide.
这里储存了翻转 优先级 调色板 图块号 纵坐标 和低8位横坐标
Here is stored the flipping, prioriy, palette, tile number, Y position, and the lower 8 bits
of the X position.
这些通常称为X位置 Y位置 图块和属性字节
These are commonly known as the X position, Y position, tile, and attribute bytes.
图块号的最高位有时被称为精灵页码
The highest bit of the tile number is sometimes known as the sprite page number, since it's
因为它与其他属性混合在一起 并确定对象使用的是前256个图块
mixed with the other attributes and determines if the object uses a tile from the first 256
还是后面256个图块
tiles or the last 256.
在表B中 每个对象条目2位宽
In table B, each object has an entry 2 bits wide.
X位置的高位 和 图块的尺寸
The highest bit of the X position and the tile's size are stored here.
当将对象绘制到屏幕上时 有一些事情需要记住
When drawing the objects onto the screen, there are a few things to keep in mind.
OAM中排前面的对象优先于具有相同优先级的后续对象
The objects earlier in OAM are prioritized over later objects with the same priority bits.
对象0在上面 对象127在下面
Normally object 0 is on top, and object 127 is on the bottom.
但是存在一个对象优先级旋转特性 它决定在上面绘制哪个对象
But there exists an object priority rotation feature, which determines witch object is
就像对象0一样
drawn on top, acting like object 0.
当对象在重叠时发生闪烁时 这是非常有用的
This is useful for when objects should flicker when overlapping, and takes care of some of
处理一些必要的的改组
the shuffling that would be necessary to implement that.
有共128个对象的限制 也有一些其他的限制
There is a limit of 128 objects in total, but there are also some other limitations.
在同一扫描线上最多只能看到32个对象
There can only be a maximum of 32 objects visible on a given scan line.
当超过32个时 只取最高优先级的32个 其他的则被丢弃
When there are more than 32, only the highest priority 32 are drawn, and the others are
discarded.
此外 同一扫描线上最多只能看到34个8x8的图块
In addition, there can only be a maximum of 34 8x8 tiles visible on a given scan line.
如果有更多 一样 只有高优先级的会被绘制
When there are more, again, only the highest priority ones are drawn.
这可能导致对象只绘制一部分 尤其是大尺寸的
This can result in an object only being half drawn, especially if it's of large size.
所有的128个对象在每一帧都绘制
All 128 objects are drawn on every frame.
有意丢弃对象的官方方法是 将他们移除屏幕就不会被看到了
The official way of purposefully discarding an object is to move it offscreen so it can't
be seen.
小的物体可以放置在屏幕下方 但大的物体需要放置在左侧或右侧
Smaller objects can be placed below the screen, but larger ones need to be placed to the left
因为屏幕上方的缓冲区太小
or right since the buffer zone above the screen is too small.
一如既往 谢谢您的观看
As always, thank you for watching.
下次我们将讨论背景层并介绍一些渲染细节
Next time we'll talk about background layers and introduce some rendering specifics.